Chapter 92.
Amberress.
Now, this amberress is a very curious substance and so important as an article
of commerce that in 1791 a certain Nantucketborn captain coffin was
examined at the bar of the English House of Commons on the subject. For at that
time, and indeed until a comparatively late day, the precise origin of
amberress remained like amber itself a problem to the learned. Though the word
amberress is but a French compound for gray amber, yet the two substances are
quite distinct. For amber, though at times found on the sea coast, is also
dug up in some far inland soils, whereas amberress is never found except upon the
sea. Besides, amber is a hard, transparent, brittle, odorless substance
used for mouthpieces to pipes, for beads and ornaments. But amberress is soft,
waxy and so highly fragrant and spicy that it is largely used in perfumery in
pastels, precious candles, hair powders and pomatum. The Turks use it in cooking
and also carry it to Mecca for the same purpose that frankincense is carried to
St. Peter's in Rome. Some wine merchants drop a few grains into clarret to flavor it.
Who would think then that such fine ladies and gentlemen should regail
themselves with an essence found in the inglorious bowels of a sick whale? Yet
so it is. By some amberress is supposed to be the cause and by others the effect
of the disyspsia in the whale. How to cure such a disspyspsia? It were hard to
say, unless by administering three or four boatloads of brandth pills, and
then running out of harm's way, as laborers do in blasting rocks.
I have forgotten to say that there were found in this amberress certain hard
round bony plates which at first Stub thought might be sailor's trousers
buttons, but afterwards it turned out that they were nothing more than pieces
of small squid bones inbalmed in that manner.
Now that the incorruption of this most fragrant amberress should be found in
the heart of such decay, is this nothing? Beth think thee of that saying
of St. Paul in Corinthians about corruption and incorruption. How that we
are sown in dishonor but raised in glory. And likewise call to mind that
saying of paracelus about what it is that maketh the best musk. Also forget
not the strange fact that of all things of ill savor, cologne water in its
rudimental manufacturing stages is the worst.
I should like to conclude the chapter with the above appeal, but cannot, owing
to my anxiety to repel a charge often made against Whaleman, and which, in the
estimation of some already biased minds, might be considered as indirectly
substantiated by what has been said of the Frenchman's two whales. Elsewhere in
this volume, the slanderous espersion has been disproved, that the vocation of
whailing is throughout a slatterly untidy business. But there is another
thing to rebut. They hint that all whales always smell bad. Now, how did
this odious stigma originate?
I upon that it is plainly traceable to the first arrival of the Greenland
whailing ships in London more than two centuries ago. Because those whalemen
did not then and do not now try out their oil at sea as the southern ships
have always done, but cutting up the fresh blubber into small bits, thrust it
through the bung holes of large casks, and carry it home in that manner. The
shortness of the season in those icy seas and the sudden and violent storms
to which they are exposed forbidding any other course. The consequence is that
upon breaking into the hold and unloading one of these whale cemeteries
in the Greenland dock, a saver is given forth somewhat similar to that arising
from excavating an old city graveyard for the foundations of a lying hospital.
I partly surmise also that this wicked charge against whalers may be likewise
imputed to the existence on the coast of Greenland in former times of a Dutch
village called Schmearrenburgg or Smeirnberg which latter name is the one
used by the learned Fogo von Slack in his great work on smells a textbook on
that subject as its name imports smear fat berg to put up this village was
founded in order to afford a place for the blubber of the Dutch whale fleet to
be tried out without being taken home to Holland for that purpose. It was a
collection of furnaces, fat kettles, and oil sheds, and when the works were in
full operation, certainly gave forth no very pleasant savor. But all this is
quite different with a South Sea sperm whaler, which in a voyage of four years,
perhaps after completely filling her hold with oil, does not perhaps consume
50 days in the business of boiling out, and in the state that it is cast, the
oil is nearly scentless. The truth is that living or dead, if but decently
treated, whales as a species, are by no means creatures of ill odor. Nor can
whaleman be recognized as the people of the Middle Ages affected to detect a Jew
in the company by the nose. Nor indeed can the whale possibly be otherwise than
fragrant, when, as a general thing he enjoys such high health, taking
abundance of exercise, always out ofdoors, though it is true, seldom in
the open air. I say that the motion of a sperm whale's flukes above water,
dispenses a perfume, as when a muskscented lady rustles her dress in a
warm parlor. What then shall I liken the sperm whale to for fragrance considering
his magnitude? Must it not be to that famous elephant with jeweled tusks and
redolent with myrr, which was led out of an Indian town to do honor to Alexander the Great.